Hey everyone, ready to seriously level up your English game?
みんな、英語力を本気でレベルアップする準備はできた？
Today we're not just going to learn some boring grammar rule, nope!
今日は退屈な文法ルールを学ぶんじゃないよ！
We are unlocking a language superpower.
言語のスーパーパワーを解放するんだ。
It's a secret tense that literally lets you travel through time and sound way more natural.
それは、時間を旅する秘密の時制で、より自然に聞こえるようになる。
Let's dive in and get this skill unlocked.
さあ、始めてこのスキルを解放しよう。
Okay, to kick things off, let's start with a classic mystery.
まずは、クラシックなミステリーから始めよう。
I want you to imagine our friend Bob.
友達のボブを想像してみて。
See, Bob had a back, and now it's gone. Poof, vanished into thin air.
ボブにはバックがあったけど、今は消えちゃった。ポン、消えた。
So what happened?
何が起こったの？
Well, in English, the answer to that question isn't just what you say.
英語では、その質問の答えは言い方にあるんだ。
It's all about how you say it. So take a look at these two sentences.
この2つの文を見てみて。
At first glance, they look almost exactly the same, right?
一見、ほとんど同じに見えるよね？
I mean, it's just one tiny little extra word. But here's the secret.
ほんの小さな単語が一つだけ違う。でも、これが秘密なんだ。
That one word changes everything.
その一言が全てを変える。
It's a clue that tells us a completely different story.
それは、全く違う物語を教えてくれる手がかりなんだ。
Stick with me, and I promise,
ついてきて、約束するよ、
you're going to be the detective who solves this case every single time.
君はこの事件を毎回解決する探偵になるから。
So what is this secret clue? What's the magic trick here?
その秘密の手がかりは何？魔法のトリックは？
Well, it's a special verb tense that I like to call the time-traveling tense.
それは、私が「時間旅行の時制」と呼ぶ特別な動詞の時制だ。
And why do I call it that? Simple.
なぜそう呼ぶかって？簡単だよ。
Because it doesn't just talk about the past.
過去だけを話すわけじゃないから。
It actually builds a bridge, a bridge from something that already happened, all the
実際には、過去の出来事から今この瞬間までの橋を架けるんだ。
way to this very moment, to right now.
ここでの大事なポイントは、現在完了形はつながりに関するものだ。
You see, the big idea here is that the present perfect is all about connection.
過去と現在をつなげる。
It connects the past to the present.
何かが以前に起こったけど、今も重要で影響があるときに使う。
You use it when something that happened before still matters, still has an effect
こう考えてみて。1時間前に宿題を終えた。それが過去。
right now.
でも結果は？今はゲームができる。ほら、そのつながり。
Think of it like this. You finished your homework an hour ago. That's the past.
これがこの時制の本質なんだ。そして、最も良い部分は、
But what's the result? You're free to play video games now. See? That connection.
この時間旅行の橋を作るのがとても簡単なこと。
That's what this tense is all about. And you know what? The best part is how easy it is to
魔法の公式はこれだ。必要なのは2つの小さなものだけ。
build this time-traveling bridge. Here's the magic formula. You just need two little things.
「have」と動詞の過去分詞。例えば、seen、eaten、gone。
The word have and the past participle of a verb. You know these words, like seen, eaten, gone.
あ、もちろん、彼や彼女、ボブのような友達にはVIPバージョンを使う。
Oh, and of course, don't forget.
「has」。それだけ。簡単でしょ？さあ、これを見て。
For our friends like he, she, or our guy Bob, we roll out the VIP version.
ここで本当に力を感じられる。
Has. And that's it. Simple, right? And check this out.
「I have lived in London for eight years」と言ったら。
This is where you can really see the power.
このタイムラインを見て。
If I say, I have lived in London for eight years.
ロンドンでの生活は過去の古い話じゃない。
Just look at this timeline.
8年前に始まったんだ。
It shows my life in London isn't just some old story from the past, no way.
その線は今の明るい瞬間まで伸びている。
It started way back then, eight years ago.
それはどういう意味？まだ続いているということ。
And that line stretches all the way up to that bright glowing now.
物語はまだ終わっていない。
What does that mean? It means I'm still there.
さて、基本的な力を手に入れたので、これが何をできるか見てみよう。
The story isn't finished yet.
現在完了形には実際に3つの主なスキルがある。
Okay, so now that we've got the basic power, let's see what this thing can really do.
それを3つの魔法の扉として考えてみて。準備はいい？
The present perfect actually has three main skills, three special abilities.
一つずつ開けてみよう。さあ、1つ目の扉。
I want you to think of them as three magic doors. You ready?
その裏には継続の力がある。
Let's open them up one by one. Alright, door number one.
これは、過去のある時点から始まり、今も続いていることに使う。
Behind it, we find the power of continuation.
この感覚は分かるよね。
This is for anything that started sometime in the past, but is still going on, still true
例えば、中学1年生からサッカー部に入っているときのように。
today. I know you know this feeling.
これがその力の実例だ。
It's when you say in Japanese, like maybe you've been in the soccer club since your
もう一つの例を見てみよう、ジェーンの場合。
first year of junior high, right? That's this power in action.
文Aでは「ジェーンは2年前にロンドンに滞在した」とある。
Let's look at another example with Jane.
それはいい思い出だけど、終わったこと。
In sentence A, it says, Jane stayed in London two years ago.
文Bでは「ジェーンは6年間ロンドンに滞在している」。
Okay, that's cool. A little trip, a memory, it happened, it's over.
おお、それは全く違う人生の物語だね。
that sentence be, Jane has stayed in London for six years.
このビジュアルがそれを明確に示している。
Whoa, that is a completely different life story, isn't it?
「滞在」はタイムライン上の単なる点。
And this visual just makes it crystal clear.
過去の一点、終わったこと。
But has stayed, that's a long unbroken line
しかし、これは6年前から続く長い線です。
that starts six years ago and connects all the way to,
それは今までつながっています。
you got it, now. It means she's still living there today.
つまり、彼女は今もそこに住んでいるということです。
Okay, you ready for magic door number two? Let's do it.
さて、魔法の扉2に準備はいいですか？行きましょう。
This is the power of experience.
これが経験の力です。
This is how you talk about your life's highlight reel,
これがあなたの人生のハイライトを語る方法です。
all the cool things you've done,
あなたがやってきた素晴らしいこと、
the places you've seen, the food you've eaten,
見た場所、食べた食べ物、
from the day you were born all the way up to right this second.
生まれた日から今までのことです。
This is your shita koto ga aru power.
これがあなたの「したことがある」パワーです。
Think about a really great anime movie.
素晴らしいアニメ映画を思い浮かべてください。
Sentence A says, I watched the movie two years ago.
文Aは「2年前に映画を見ました」と言います。
Okay, that just tells us when you did it.
それはいつ見たかを教えているだけです。
but sentence B, I have watched the movie three times.
でも文Bは「映画を3回見た」と言います。
See, that's not about when, that's about your life's total score.
これはいつではなく、あなたの人生の総合的なスコアです。
It's like your personal record.
まるで個人記録のようです。
And this timeline shows it perfectly.
このタイムラインがそれを完璧に示しています。
Watched is just one little event in your past, but have watched?
「見た」は過去の小さな出来事ですが、「見たことがある」は？
That's like collecting achievements in a video game.
それはビデオゲームの実績を集めるようなものです。
You get one here, another one here, and another one over here,
ここで一つ、またここで一つ、さらにここで一つ、
and they all add up to your total life experience right now.
それらはすべて今のあなたの人生経験に加算されます。
And that brings us to the third and final door.
そして、これが3つ目で最後の扉です。
And listen up, because this one is super, super important.
よく聞いてください、これは非常に重要です。
It's the power of result.
結果の力です。
This is for when something happened in the past, and
これは過去に何かが起こり、
because of that one thing, everything is different now.
その一つの出来事によって、今すべてが変わった時です。
It's that feeling of, shite shimai mashita, where the
それは「してしまった」という感覚で、
consequence of the action is the whole point of the story.
行動の結果が物語の全てのポイントです。
So remember our friend Bob and his mystery?
ボブとその謎を思い出してください。
Well, we can finally solve it.
さて、ついに解決できます。
If you say Bob lost his bag, well, that's just a fact
「ボブはバッグを失くした」と言ったら、それはただの事実です。
From the past, maybe he found it five minutes later, who knows, the story's over.
過去のことかもしれません、もしかしたら5分後に見つけたかもしれません。
But if you say Bob has lost his bag, uh- oh, that's different.
でも「ボブはバッグを失くしてしまった」と言ったら、ああ、それは違います。
The result is clear.
結果は明確です。
He's standing right there, right now, probably looking super worried with no bag in his hands.
彼は今、そこに立っていて、バッグを持っていないので、非常に心配そうです。
The problem is happening now, mystery solved.
問題は今起こっていて、謎は解決しました。
You know, this result power is actually all around us in real life.
この結果の力は実際に私たちの周りにあります。
Let's look at a delicious example from Japan that I'm pretty sure everybody knows.
日本の美味しい例を見てみましょう。みんな知っていると思います。
It explains this idea perfectly.
このアイデアを完璧に説明しています。
Come on, you've all seen this sign in the summer, right?
夏にこの看板を見たことがありますよね？
Hayashi Chuka Hajimemashita. Believe it or not, this sign is secretly
「林中華始めました」。信じられないかもしれませんが、この看板は
a perfect English lesson. It's the present perfect result power
完璧な英語のレッスンです。現在完了の結果の力が
hiding in plain sight. Let's break it down. It's so simple.
目の前に隠れています。分解してみましょう。とても簡単です。
Step one, the restaurant started making Hayashi Chuka. When?
ステップ1、レストランが林中華を作り始めました。いつ？
I don't know, last week, this morning? Honestly, it doesn't matter.
わかりません、先週？今朝？正直、重要ではありません。
The important part, the result for us hungry people is step two.
重要なのは、私たち空腹な人々にとっての結果はステップ2です。
we can walk in and order it right now.
今すぐ入って注文できることです。
The past action created a delicious present reality.
過去の行動が美味しい現在の現実を生み出しました。
Okay, this is a fun one.
さて、これは面白いです。
What do you think the American version of this is?
アメリカ版は何だと思いますか？
Or like the global version? What's something that starts in the past
あるいはグローバル版は？過去に始まり、
and the awesome result is that you get to enjoy it now. Any ideas?
その素晴らしい結果が今楽しめるものは何ですか？アイデアはありますか？
Boom, here it is. Every single time you open up Netflix
はい、これです。Netflixを開くたびに、
or YouTube or Disney Plus and you see that big now streaming sign,
YouTubeやDisney Plusで「今ストリーミング中」のサインを見た時、
it is the exact same idea.
まったく同じアイデアです。
the streaming service has added a new movie.
ストリーミングサービスが新しい映画を追加しました。
The action happened in the past and the result,
その行動は過去に起こり、結果は、
you can grab some popcorn and watch it now.
今、ポップコーンを持って見ることができるということです。
It's basically the entertainment version of Cold Noodles.
基本的に、エンターテインメント版の冷やし中華です。
Wow, look at how far we've come.
さあ、私たちがどれだけ進んできたか見てください。
We have traveled through time, we've solved a mystery
私たちは時間を旅し、謎を解きました。
and we've even talked about delicious food and movies.
美味しい食べ物や映画についても話しました。
So let's just do a quick final review
では、最後に振り返りましょう。
of our amazing bridge from the past to the present.
過去から現在への素晴らしい架け橋です。
Here they are, your three brand new language superpowers.
こちらが、あなたの新しい言語スーパーパワーです。
continuation for things that are still going on,
進行中のことについての継続、
experience so you can talk about your awesome life story,
素晴らしい人生の物語を語るための経験、
and result for when the past totally changes the present.
そして、過去が現在を変える結果です。
You've officially unlocked them all.
すべてを正式に手に入れました。
But listen, if you only remember one thing,
でも、もし一つだけ覚えるなら、
one secret code from our whole mission today,
今日のミッションからの秘密のコードは、
make it this, the present perfect is always,
現在完了形は常に、
always connected to now. That's it. That's it's one and only rule.
今とつながっているということです。それが唯一のルールです。
It's the golden key to using it perfectly every single time.
完璧に使うための黄金の鍵です。
So I'm gonna leave you with a little challenge.
では、ちょっとした挑戦を残します。
What's your have done story? What amazing video games have you played?
あなたの「したこと」の物語は何ですか？どんな素晴らしいゲームをしましたか？
What's the best manga you have ever read?
今まで読んだ中で最高の漫画は何ですか？
Start using this time traveling tense to talk about your own life
この時間旅行の時制を使って、自分の人生について話してみてください。
and I'm telling you, you will master it in no time.
すぐにマスターできると思います。
You guys did awesome today.
皆さん、今日は素晴らしかったです。